Register of the Alexander Yvanoff (Aleksandr Efimovich Ivanov) Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alexander Yvanoff (Aleksandr Efimovich Ivanov) papers
1957-1976
2000C80
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Memoirs, correspondence, and photographs, relating to the Russian Civil War, Russian émigré life in the Philippines, and guerrilla activities in the Philippines during World War II.
Yvanoff, Alexander, 1896-1973
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Yvanoff was born in Kazan' on 20 January 1896. As an ensign (praporshchik) in the Russian army in 1917, he witnessed the collapse of the front, and returned to Kazan', where he joined the anti-Bolshevik army in 1918. He remained with the Whites till his evacuation from Vladivostok with Admiral Iu. K. Stark's flotilla in October 1922.
A fluke of fate left him stranded in the Philippines (instead of continuing on to the United States as had been his intention), and there he remained, working as a logger, surveyor, and miner.
During the Second World War, he fought with guerrilla forces against the Japanese, and spent the post-war years locating and defusing bombs and landmines left in the Philippines. Yvanoff died in Zamboanga on 25 January 1973. He described his life in a memoir entitled "From Kazan to Zamboanga," recorded by Ann Evans, the wife of a mining engineer for whom Yvanoff had worked.
Chronology
1896 January 20 Born, Kazan', Russia
1917 Ensign (Praporshchik), Russian Army
1922 Left Vladivostok for the Philippines
1930 October 6 Married Petronila Brown
1941-1945 Fought the Japanese in the Philippines in a guerrilla unit
1973 January 25 Died, Zamboanga, Philippines
Scope and Content Note
The piece de resistance of this collection is Yvanoff's memoir, "Kazan' to Zamboanga," detailing his family history, participation in the Russian Civil War in Siberia and the Far East, evacuation to the Philippines and life there, including participation in anti-Japanese guerrilla warfare during World War II.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Philippines--History--Japanese occupation, 1942-1945.; Philippines.; Russia.; Russians--Philippines.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographical File, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Article about Yvanoff, with related correspondance, and clippings
- Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Writings, 1972 (Box 1)
  Memoirs entitled "Kazan' to Zamboanga"
- Photographs, 1957-1973 (Box 1)
  Eleven prints depicting Yvanoff and family members
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
  - Article about Yvanoff from Sunburst magazine,, with associated correspondence, 1976 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings
    - About Yvanoff (Folder 1: 2)
    - On various subjects with notes and commentary by Yvanoff (Folder 1: 3)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1967-1973
  - Bourret, W., 1973 and undated (Folder 1: 4)
  - Evans, Hugh and Ann, 1967-1973 (Folder 1: 5)
    General note
    See also WRITINGS
    Much of the correspondence relates to Ann Evans' typing and editing of Yvanoff's memoirs.
  - Soviet Union. Posol'stvo (Japan), 1971 (Folder 1: 6)
- WRITINGS, 1972
  See also CORRESPONDENCE/Evans, Hugh and Ann
  Memoirs typed and edited by Ann G. Evans, entitled "Kazan' to Zamboanga," 1972.
  - Holograph (incomplete) (Folder 1: 7-8)
  - Typescript
    - Rough draft, with Yvanoff's corrections (Folder 1: 9)
    - Final draft (Folder 1: 10)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1957-1973 (Folder 1: 11)